I guess we should do an intro to to this as well,
so this is a just sort of a
free-form Q&A lecture where you, as in
the two people sitting here, but also
everyone at home who did not come here
in person get to ask questions and we
have a bunch of questions people asked
in advance but you can also ask
additional questions during, for the two
of you who are here, you can do it either
by raising your hand or you can submit it on
the forum and be anonymous, it's up to you
regardless though, what we're gonna
do is just go through some of the
questions have been asked and try to
give as helpful answers as we can
although they are unprepared on our side and
yeah that's the plan I guess we go
from popular to least popular
fire away
all right so for our first question any
recommendations on learning operating
system related topics like processes,
virtual memory, interrupts,
memory management, etc
so I think this is a
is an interesting question because these
are really low level concepts that often
do not matter, unless you have to
deal with this in some capacity,
right so
one instance where this matters is you're
writing really low level code like
you're implementing a kernel or something
like that, or you want to
just hack on the Linux kernel.
It's rare otherwise that you need to work with
especially like virtual memory and
interrupts and stuff yourself
processes, I think are a more general concept
that we've talked a little bit about in
this class as well and tools like
htop, pgrep, kill, and signals and
that sort of stuff
in terms of learning it
maybe one of the best ways, is to try to
take either an introductory class on the
topic, so for example MIT has a class
called 6.828, which is where
you essentially build and develop your
own operating system based on some code
that you're given, and all of those labs
are publicly available and all the
resources for the class are publicly available,
and so that is a good way to
really learn them is by doing them yourself.
There are also various
tutorials online that basically guide
you through how do you write a kernel
from scratch. Not necessarily a very
elaborate one, not one you would want
to run any real software on, but just to
teach you the basics and so that would
be another thing to look up.
Like how do I write a kernel in and then your
language of choice. You will probably not
find one that lets you do it in Python
but in like C, C++, Rust, there
are a bunch of topics like this
one other note on operating systems
so like Jon mentioned MIT has a 6.828 class but
if you're looking for a more high-level
overview, not necessarily programming or
an operating system, but just learning about
the concepts another good resource
is a book called "Modern Operating
Systems" by Andy Tannenbaum
there's also actually a book called the "The FreeBSD
Operating System" which is really good,
It doesn't go through Linux, but it goes
through FreeBSD and the BSD kernel is
arguably better organized than the Linux
one and better documented and so it
might be a gentler introduction to some of those
topics than trying to understand Linux
You want to check it as answered?
- Yes + Nice
Answered
For our next question
What are some of the tools you'd
prioritize learning first?
- Maybe we can all go through and
give our opinion on this? + Yeah
Tools to prioritize learning first?
I think learning your editor well,
just serves you in all capacities
like being efficient at editing files,
is just like a majority of
what you're going to spend your time doing.
And in general, just using your
keyboard more in your mouse less. It means
that you get to spend more of your
time doing useful things and
less of your time moving
I think that would be my top priority,
so I would say that for what
tool to prioritize will depend
on what exactly you're doing
I think the core idea is you should try
to find the types of tasks that you are
doing repetitively and so
if you are doing some sort of like
machine learning workload and
you find yourself using jupyter notebooks,
like the one we presented
yesterday, a lot. Then again, using
a mouse for that might not be
the best idea and you want to familiarize
with the keyboard shortcuts
and pretty much with anything you will
end up figuring out that there are some
repetitive tasks, and you're running a
computer, and just trying to figure out
oh there's probably a better way to do this
be it a terminal, be it an editor
And it might be really interesting to
learn to use some of the topics that
we have covered, but if they're not
extremely useful in a everyday
basis then it might not worth prioritizing them
out of the topics
covered in this class in my opinion two
of the most useful things are version
control and text editors, and I think they're
a little bit different from each
other, in the sense that text editors I
think are really useful to learn well
but it was probably the case that before
we started using vim and all its fancy
keyboard shortcuts you had some other
text editor you were using before and
you could edit text just fine maybe a little
bit inefficiently whereas I think
version control is another really useful
skill and that's one where if you don't
really know the tool properly, it can actually
lead to some problems like loss
of data or just inability to collaborate
properly with people so I
think version control is one of the first
things that's worth learning well
yeah, I agree with that, I think
learning a tool like Git is just
gonna save you so much heartache down the line
it also, to add on to that
It really helps you collaborate with others
and Anish touched a little bit on GitHub
in the last lecture, and just learning
to use that tool well in order
to work on larger software projects
that other people are working on is
an invaluable skill
For our next question
when do I use Python versus a
bash script, versus some other language
This is tough, because I think this comes
down to what Jose was saying earlier too
that it really depends on
what you're trying to do
For me, I think for bash scripts in particular
bash scripts are for
automating running a bunch of commands,
you don't want to write any
other like business logic in bash
it is just for I want to run these
commands, in this order. Maybe with
arguments, but like even that
it's unclear do you want to bash script
once you start taking arguments
Similarly, once you start doing any
kind of like text processing or
configuration, all that
reach for a language that is a more serious
programming language than bash is
bash is really for sort of short one-off
scripts or ones that have a very well-defined
use case on the terminal in
the shell, probably
For a slightly more concrete guideline,
you might say write a
bash script if it's less than a hundred
lines of code or so, but once it gets
beyond that point bash is kind of
unwieldy and it's probably worth
switching to a more serious programming
language like Python
and to add to that
I would say that I found myself writing
sometimes scripts in Python because
If I have already solved some subproblem
that covers part of the problem in Python
I find it much easier to compose the
previous solution that I found out in
Python and just try to reuse bash code,
that I don't find as reusable as Python
And in the same way it's kind of nice that
a lot of people have written something
like Python libraries or like Ruby libraries
to do a lot of these things
whereas in bash is kind of hard
to have like code reuse
And in fact,
I think to add to that. Usually, if you
find a library in some language that
helps with the task you're trying to
do, use that language for the job
And in bash there are no libraries, there
are only the programs on your computer
So you probably don't want to use
it unless like there's a program
you can just invoke I do think another
thing worth remembering about bash
bash is really hard to get right.
It's very easy to get it right for the particular
use case you're trying to solve right now
but things like
What if one of the filenames has a space in it?
It has caused so many bugs and so
many problems in bash scripts and if you
use a real programming language then
those problems just go away
Checked it
For our next question
What is the difference between sourcing
a script and executing that script ?
So this actually, we got in office
hours a while back as well which is
Aren't they the same? like aren't they
both just running the bash script?
and it is true
both of these will end up executing the
lines of code that are in the script
the ways in which they differ is that
sourcing a script is telling your
current bash script, your current bash
session to execute that program
whereas the other one is, start up a new instance
of bash and run the program there instead
And this matters for things like imagine that
"script.sh" tries to change directories
If you are running the script
as in the second invocation
"./script.sh", then the new
process is going to change
directories but by the time that script
exits and returns to your shell
your shell still remains in the same place. However,
if you do CD in a script and you source it
Your current instance of bash is the
one that ends up running it and
so it ends up CDing where you are
This is also why if you define functions
For example, that you may want to
execute in your shell session
You need to source the script, not run it
Because if you run it, that function
will be defined in the
instance of bash
In the bash process that gets launched but it
will not be defined in your current shell
I think those are two of the biggest
differences between the two
Next question,
What are the places where various packages and tools
are stored and how does referencing them work?
What even is /bin or /lib?
So as we covered in the first lecture,
there is this PATH environment variable
which is a semicolon separated
string of all the places
where your shell is gonna look for binaries
and if you just do something
like "echo $PATH", you're gonna get this list
and all these places are gonna
be consulted in order.
It's gonna go through all of them and in fact
- There is already... Did we cover which? + Yeah
So if you run "which" and a specific command
the shell is actually is gonna tell
you where it's finding this
Beyond that,
there is like some conventions where a lot
of programs will install their binaries
and they're like /usr/bin (or at
least they will include symlinks)
in /usr/bin so you can find them
There's also a /usr/local/bin
There are special directories. For example,
/usr/sbin it's only for sudo user and
some of these conventions are slightly
different between different distros so
I know like some distros for example install
the user libraries under /opt for example
Yeah I think one thing just
to talk a little bit of more
about /bin and then Anish maybe you can
do the other folders so when it comes to
/bin the convention
There are conventions, and the conventions are
usually /bin are for essential system utilities
/usr/bin are for user programs and
/usr/local/bin are for user
compiled programs, sort of
so things that you installed that you intend
the user to run, are in /usr/bin
things that a user has compiled themselves and stuck
on your system, probably goes in /usr/local/bin
but again, this varies a lot from machine
to machine, and distro to distro
On Arch Linux, for example, /bin
is a symlink to /usr/bin
They're the same and as Jose mentioned, there's
also /sbin which is for programs that are
intended to only be run as root, that
also varies from distro to distro
whether you even have that directory, and
on many systems like /usr/local/bin
might not even be in your PATH, or
might not even exist on your system
On BSD on the other hand /usr/local/bin
is often used a lot more heavily
yeah so
What we were talking about so far, these
are all ways that files and folders are
organized on Linux things or Linux or
BSD things vary a little bit between
that and macOS or other platforms
I think for the specific locations,
if you to know exactly what it's
used for, you can look it up
But some general patterns to keep in mind or anything
with /bin in it has binary executable programs in it,
anything with \lib in it, has
libraries in it so things that
programs can link against, and then some
other things that are useful to know are
there's a /etc on many systems, which
has configuration files in it and
then there's /home, which underneath that directory
contains each user's home directory
so like on a linux box my username
or if it's Anish will
correspond to a home directory /home/anish
Yeah I guess there are
a couple of others like /tmp is usually
a temporary directory that gets
erased when you reboot not always but sometimes,
you should check on your system
There's a /var which often holds like
files the change over time so
these these are usually going to be things
like lock files for package managers
they're gonna be things like log files
files to keep track of process IDs
then there's /dev which shows devices so
usually so these are special files that
correspond to devices on your system we
talked about /sys, Anish mentioned /etc
/opt is a common one for just like third-party
software that basically it's usually for
companies ported their software to Linux
but they don't actually understand what
running software on Linux is like, and
so they just have a directory with all
their stuff in it and when those get installed
they usually get installed into /opt
I think those are the ones off the top of my head
yeah
And we will list these in our lecture notes
which will produce after this lecture
Next question
Should I apt-get install a Python whatever
package or pip install that package
so this is a good question that I think at
a higher level this question is asking
should I use my systems package manager
to install things or should I use some other
package manager. Like in this case
one that's more specific to a particular
language. And the answer here is also
kind of it depends, sometimes it's nice
to manage things using a system package
manager so everything can be installed
and upgraded in a single place but
I think oftentimes whatever is available
in the system repositories the things
you can get via a tool like
apt-get or something similar
might be slightly out of date compared to
the more language specific repository
so for example a lot of the Python packages
I use I really want the most
up-to-date version and so
I use pip to install them
Then, to extend on that is
sometimes the case the system packages
might require some other
dependencies that you might not have realized
about, and it's also might be
the case or like for some systems,
at least for like alpine Linux they
don't have wheels for like a lot of the
Python packages so it will just take
longer to compile them, it will take more
space because they have to compile them
from scratch. Whereas if you just go
to pip, pip has binaries for a lot of
different platforms and that will probably work
You also should be aware that pip might not do
the exact same thing in different computers
So, for example, if you are in a kind of laptop
or like a desktop that is running like
a x86 or x86_64 you probably have binaries,
but if you're running something
like Raspberry Pi or some other kind of
embedded device. These are running on a
different kind of hardware architecture
and you might not have binaries
I think that's also good to take into account,
in that case in might be worthwhile to
use the system packages just because they
will take much shorter to get them
than to just to compile from scratch
the entire Python installation
Apart from that, I don't think I can think of any exceptions
where I would actually use the system packages
instead of the Python provided ones
So, one other thing to keep in mind is that
sometimes you will have more than one
program on your computer and you might
be developing more than one program on
your computer and for some reason not
all programs are always built with the latest
version of things, sometimes they
are a little bit behind, and when you
install something system-wide you can
only... depends on your exact system,
but often you just have one version
what pip lets you do, especially combined
with something like python's virtualenv,
and similar concepts exist for other
languages, where you can sort of say
I want to (NPM does the same thing as well
with its node modules, for example) where
I'm gonna compile the dependencies of
this package in sort of a subdirectory
of its own, and all of the versions that it
requires are going to be built in there
and you can do this separately for separate
projects so there they have
different dependencies or the same dependencies
with different versions
they still sort of kept separate. And that
is one thing that's hard to achieve
with system packages
Next question
What's the easiest and best profiling tools
to use to improve performance of my code?
This is a topic we could talk
about for a very long time
The easiest and best is to print stuff using time
Like, I'm not joking, very often
the easiest thing is in your code
At the top you figure out what the current
time is, and then you do sort of
a binary search over your program of add
a print statement that prints how much
time has elapsed since the start of your
program and then you do that until you
find the segment of code that took the
longest. And then you go into that
function and then you do the same thing
again and you keep doing this until you
find roughly where the time was spent. It's
not foolproof, but it is really easy
and it gives you good information quickly
if you do need more advanced information
Valgrind has a tool called cache-grind?
call grind? Cache grind? One of the two.
and this tool lets you run your program and
measure how long everything takes and
all of the call stacks, like which
function called which function, and what
you end up with is a really neat
annotation of your entire program source
with the heat of every line basically
how much time was spent there. It does
slow down your program by like an order
of magnitude or more, and it doesn't really
support threads but it is really
useful if you can use it. If you can't,
then tools like perf or similar tools
for other languages that do usually some
kind of sampling profiling like we
talked about in the profiler lecture, can
give you pretty useful data quickly,
but it's a lot of data around
this, but they're a little bit
biased and what kind of things they usually
highlight as a problem and it
can sometimes be hard to extract meaningful
information about what should
I change in response to them. Whereas the
sort of print approach very quickly
gives you like this section
of code is bad or slow
I think would be my answer
Flamegraphs are great, they're a good way
to visualize some of this information
Yeah I just have one thing to add,
oftentimes programming languages
have language specific tools for profiling
so to figure out what's the
right tool to use for your language like if
you're doing JavaScript in the web browser
the web browser has a really nice tool for
doing profiling you should just use that
or if you are using go, for example, go has a built-in
profiler is really good you should just use that
A last thing to add to that
Sometimes you might find that doing this binary
search over time that you're kind of
finding where the time is going, but this
time is sometimes happening because
you're waiting on the network, or you're
waiting for some file, and in that case
you want to make sure that the time
that is, if I want to write
like 1 gigabyte file or like read 1
gigabyte file and put it into memory
you want to check that the actual time
there, is the minimum amount of time
you actually have to wait. If it's ten times
longer, you should try to use some
other tools that we covered in the debugging
and profiling section to see
why you're not utilizing all your
resources because that might...
Because that might be a lot of what's happening
thing, like for example, in my research
in machine learning workloads, a lot of
time is loading data and you have to
make sure well like the time it takes to
load data is actually the minimum amount
of time you want to have that happening
And to build on that, there are actually
specialized tools for doing things like
analyzing wait times. Very often when
you're waiting for something what's
really happening is you're issuing your
system call, and that system call takes
some amount of time to respond. Like you do
a really large write, or a really large read
or you do many of them, and one thing
that can be really handy here is
to try to get information out of the
kernel about where your program is
spending its time. And so there's (it's
not new), but there's a relatively
newly available thing called BPF or eBPF.
Which is essentially kernel tracing
and you can do some really cool things with
it, and that includes tracing user programs.
It can be a little bit awkward to
get started with, there's a tool
called BPF trace that i would recommend
you looking to, if you need to do like
this kind of low-level performance debugging.
But it is really good for this
kind of stuff. You can get things like
histograms over how much time was spent
in particular system calls
It's a great tool
What browser plugins do you use?
I try to use as few as I can get away with using
because I don't like things being in
my browser, but there are a couple of
ones that are sort of staples.
The first one is uBlock Origin.
So uBlock Origin is one of many ad blockers but
it's a little bit more than an ad blocker.
It is (a what do they call it?) a
network filtering tool so it lets
you do more things than just block ads.
It also lets you like block connections
to certain domains, block connections
for certain types of resources
So I have mine set up in what they call
the Advanced Mode, where basically
you can disable basically all network requests.
But it's not just Network requests,
It's also like I have disabled all inline
scripts on every page and all
third-party images and resources, and then
you can sort of create a whitelist
for every page so it gives you really
low-level tools around how to
how to improve the security of your browsing.
But you can also set it in not the
advanced mode, and then it does much of
the same as a regular ad blocker would
do, although in a fairly efficient way
if you're looking at an ad blocker it's
probably the one to use and it
works on like every browser
That would be my top pick I think,
I think probably the one I
use like the most actively
is one called Stylus. It lets you modify
the CSS or like the stylesheets
that webpages have. And it's pretty
neat, because sometimes you're
looking at a website and you want
to hide some part of the website
you don't care about. Like maybe a ad, maybe
some sidebar you're not finding useful
The thing is, at the end of
the day these things are
displaying in your browser, and you
have control of what code is
executing and similar to what Jon was
saying, like you can customize this
to no end, and what I have for a lot of
web pages like hide this this part, or
also trying to make like dark modes for
them like you can change pretty much the
color for every single website. And what
is actually pretty neat is that there's
like a repository online of people that
have contributed this is stylesheets
for the websites. So someone probably
has (done) one for GitHub
Like I want dark GitHub and someone has
already contributed one that makes
that much more pleasing to browse. Apart
from that, one that it's not really
fancy, but I have found incredibly helpful
is one that just takes a screenshot an
entire website. And It will
scroll for you and make
compound image of the entire website and that's
really great for when you're trying to
print a website and is just terrible.
(It's built into Firefox)
oh interesting
oh now that you mention builtin to Firefox,
another one that I really like about
Firefox is the multi account containers
(Oh yeah, it's fantastic)
Which kind of lets you
By default a lot of web browsers, like
for example Chrome, have this
notion of like there's session that you
have, where you have all your cookies
and they are kind of all shared from the
different websites in the sense of
you keep opening new tabs and unless you go into
incognito you kind of have the same profile
And that profile is the same for
all websites, there is this
Is it an extension or is it built in?
(it's a mix, it's complicated)
So I think you actually have to say you want
to install it or enable it and again
the name is Multi Account Containers and
these let you tell Firefox to have
separate isolated sessions. So
for example, you want to say
I have a separate sessions for whenever I
visit to Google or whenever I visit Amazon
and that can be pretty neat, because then you can
At a browser level it's ensuring that no information
sharing is happening between the two of them
And it's much more convenient than
having to open a incognito window
where it's gonna clean all the time the stuff
(One thing to mention is Stylus vs Stylish)
Oh yeah, I forgot about that
One important thing is the browser extension
for side loading CSS Stylesheets
it's called a Stylus and that's different
from the older one that was
called Stylish, because that one got
bought at some point by some shady
company, that started abusing it not only to have
that functionality, but also to read your
entire browser history and send that
back to their servers so they could data mine it.
So, then people just built this open-source alternative
that is called Stylus, and that's the one
we recommend. Said that, I think the repository
for styles is the same for the
two of them, but I would have
to double check that.
Do you have any browser plugins Anish?
Yes, so I also have some recommendations
for browser plugins
I also use uBlock Origin and I also use Stylus,
but one other one that I'd recommend is
integration with a password manager
So this is a topic that we have in
the lecture notes for the security
lecture, but we didn't really get to talk
about in detail. But basically password
managers do a really good job of increasing
your security when working
with online accounts, and having browser
integration with your password manager
can save you a lot of time like you
can open up a website then it can
autofill your login information for you
sir and you go and copy and paste it
back and forth between a separate program
if it's not integrated with your
web browser, and it can also, this integration,
can save you from certain
attacks that would otherwise be possible if
you were doing this manual copy pasting.
For example, phishing attacks. So
you find a website that looks very
similar to Facebook and you go to log in
with your facebook login credentials and
you go to your password manager and copy
paste the correct credentials into this
funny web site and now all of a sudden
it has your password but if you have
browser integration then the extension
can automatically check
like. Am I on F A C E B O O K.com,or
is it some other domain
that maybe look similar and it will not enter
the login information if it's the wrong domain
so browser extension for
password managing is good
Yeah I agree
Next question
What are other useful data wrangling tools?
So in yesterday's lecture, I mentioned curl, so
curl is a fantastic tool for just making web
requests and dumping them to your terminal.
You can also use it for things
like uploading files which is really handy.
In the exercises of that lecture we also talked about
JQ and pup which are command line tools that let you
basically write queries over JSON
and HTML documents respectively
that can be really handy. Other
data wrangling tools?
Ah Perl, the Perl programming language is
often referred to as a write only
programming language because it's
impossible to read even if you wrote it.
But it is fantastic at doing just like
straight up text processing, like nothing
beats it there, so maybe worth learning
some very rudimentary Perl just
to write some of those scripts
It's easier often than writing some like hacked-up
combination of grep and awk and sed,
and it will be much faster to just tack something
up than writing it up in Python, for example
but apart from that, other data wrangling
No, not off the top of my head really
column -t, if you pipe any white space separated
input into column -t it will align all
the white space of the columns so that
you get nicely aligned columns that's, and
head and tail but we talked about those
I think a couple of additions to that,
that I find myself using commonly
one is vim. Vim can be pretty useful
for like data wrangling on itself
Sometimes you might find that the operation
that you're trying to do is
hard to put down in terms of piping
different operators but if you
can just open the file and just record
a couple of quick vim macros to do what you
want it to do, it might be like much,
much easier. That's one, and then the other
one, if you're dealing with tabular
data and you want to do more complex operations
like sorting by one column,
then grouping and then computing some sort
of statistic, I think a lot of that
workload I ended up just using Python
and pandas because it's built for that
And one of the pretty neat features that
I find myself also using is that it
will export to many different formats.
So this intermediate state
has its own kind of pandas dataframe
object but it can
export to HTM, LaTeX, a lot of different
like table formats so if your end
product is some sort of summary table, then pandas
I think it's a fantastic choice for that
I would second the vim and also
Python I think those are
two of my most used data wrangling tools.
For the vim one, last year we had a demo
in the series in the lecture notes, but
we didn't cover it in class we had a
demo of turning an XML file into a JSON version
of that same data using only vim macros
And I think that's actually the
way I would do it in practice
I don't want to go find a tool that does
this conversion it is actually simple
to encode as a vim macro,
then I just do it that way
And then also Python especially in an interactive
tool like a Jupyter notebook
is a really great way of doing data wrangling
A third tool I'd mention which
I don't remember if we
covered in the data wrangling
lecture or elsewhere
is a tool called pandoc which can do transformations
between different text
document formats so you can convert from
plaintext to HTML or HTML to markdown
or LaTeX to HTML or many other formats
it actually it supports a large
list of input formats and a
large list of output formats
I think there's one last one which I mentioned briefly
in the lecture on data wrangling which is
the R programming language, it's
an awful (I think it's an awful)
language to program in. And i would never
use it in the middle of a data wrangling
pipeline, but at the end, in order to like produce
pretty plots and statistics R is great
Because R is built for doing
statistics and plotting
there's a library for are called
ggplot which is just amazing
ggplot2 i guess technically It's
great, it produces very
nice visualizations and it lets you do,
it does very easily do things like
If you have a data set that has like multiple
facets like it's not just X and Y
it's like X Y Z and some other variable,
and then you want to plot like the
throughput grouped by all of those parameters
at the same time and produce
a visualization. R very easily let's you
do this and I haven't seen anywhere
that lets you do that as easily
Next question,
What's the difference between
Docker and a virtual machine
What's the easiest way to explain this? So docker
starts something called containers and
docker is not the only program that
starts containers. There are many others
and usually they rely on some feature of
the underlying kernel in the case of
docker they use something called LXC
which are Linux containers and the basic
premise there is if you want to start
what looks like a virtual machine that
is running roughly the same operating
system as you are already running on your
computer then you don't really need
to run another instance of the kernel
really that other virtual machine can
share a kernel. And you can just use the
kernels built in isolation mechanisms to
spin up a program that thinks it's
running on its own hardware but in
reality it's sharing the kernel and so this
means that containers can often run
with much lower overhead than a full virtual
machine will do but you should
keep in mind that it also has somewhat weaker
isolation because you are sharing
a kernel between the two if you spin up
a virtual machine the only thing that's
shared is sort of the hardware and to
some extent the hypervisor, whereas
with a docker container you're sharing
the full kernel and the that is a
different threat model that you
might have to keep in mind
One another small note there as Jon pointed
out, to use containers something
like Docker you need the underlying operating
system to be roughly the same
as whatever the program that's running
on top of the container expects and so
if you're using macOS for example, the
way you use docker is you run Linux
inside a virtual machine and then you can
run Docker on top of Linux so maybe
if you're going for containers in order
to get better performance your trading
isolation for performance if you're running
on Mac OS that may not work out
exactly as expected
And one last note is that there
is a slight difference, so
with Docker and containers,
one of the gotchas you have
to be familiar with is that containers
are more similar to virtual
machines in the sense of that they will
persist all the storage that you
have where Docker by default won't have that.
Like Docker is supposed to be running
So the main idea is like I want
to run some software and
I get the image and it runs and if you
want to have any kind of persistent
storage that links to the host system
you have to kind of manually specify
that, whereas a virtual machine is using
some virtual disk that is being provided
Next question
What are the advantages of each operating system
and how can we choose between them?
For example, choosing the best Linux
distribution for our purposes
I will say that for many, many tasks the
specific Linux distribution that you're
running is not that important
the thing is, it's just what kind of
knowing that there are different types
or like groups of distributions,
So for example, there are some distributions
that have really frequent updates
but they kind of break more easily. So for
example Arch Linux has a rolling update
way of pushing updates, where things might
break but they're fine with the things
being that way. Where maybe where you
have some really important web server
that is hosting all your business
analytics you want that thing
to have like a much more steady way of
updates. So that's for example why you
will see distributions like Debian being
much more conservative about what they push, or
even for example Ubuntu makes a difference
between the Long Term Releases
that they are only update every
two years and the more periodic
releases of one there is a
it's like two a year that they make.
So, kind of knowing that there's the
difference apart from that some distributions
have different ways
of providing the binaries
to you and the way they
have the repositories so I think a lot of Red
Hat Linux don't want non free drivers in
their official repositories where I
think Ubuntu is fine with some of
them, apart from that I think like just
a lot of what is core to most Linux
distros is kind of shared between them
and there's a lot of learning in the
common ground. So you don't have
to worry about the specifics
Keeping with the theme of this class being somewhat
opinionated, I'm gonna go ahead and say
that if you're using Linux especially for
the first time choose something like
Ubuntu or Debian. So you Ubuntu to is a
Debian based distribution but maybe is a
little bit more friendly, Debian is a little
bit more minimalist. I use Debian
and all my servers, for example. And I use
Debian desktop on my desktop computers
that run Linux if you're going for maybe
trying to learn more things and you want
a distribution that trades stability for
having more up-to-date software maybe
at the expense of you having to fix a
broken distribution every once in a
while then maybe you can consider something
like Arch Linux or Gentoo
or Slackware. Oh man, I'd say that like
if you're installing Linux and just like
want to get work done Debian is a great choice
Yeah I think I agree with that.
The other observation is like
you couldn't install BSD
BSD has gotten, has come a long way from
where it was. There's still a bunch of
software you can't really get for BSD but
it gives you a very well-documented
experience and and one thing that's different
about BSD compared to Linux is
that in an BSD when you install BSD you
get a full operating system, mostly
So many of the programs are maintained by
the same team that maintains the kernel
and everything is sort of upgraded together,
which is a little different
than how thanks work in the Linux world it does
mean that things often move a little bit
slower. I would not use it for things
like gaming either, because drivers support
is meh. But it is an interesting
environment to look at. And then for things
like Mac OS and Windows I think
If you are a programmer, I don't know why
you are using Windows unless you are
building things for Windows; or you want
to be able to do gaming and stuff
but in that case, maybe try dual booting,
even though that's a pain too
Mac OS is a is a good sort of middle point
between the two where you get a system
that is like relatively nicely polished
for you. But you still have access to
some of the lower-level bits
at least to a certain extent.
it's also really easy to dual boot Mac OS and Windows
it is not quite the case with like Mac OS and
Linux or Linux and Windows
Alright, for the rest of the
questions so these are
all 0 upvote questions so maybe we can go
through them quickly in the last five
or so minutes of class. So the next
one is Vim versus Emacs? Vim!
Easy answer, but a more serious answer is like I think
all three of us use vim as our primary editor
I use Emacs for some research specific
stuff which requires Emacs but
at a higher level both editors have interesting
ideas behind them and if you
have the time is worth exploring both
to see which fits you better and also
you can use Emacs and run it in a vim
emulation mode. I actually know a
good number of people who do that so
they get access to some of the cool
Emacs functionality and some of the cool
philosophy behind that like Emacs is
programmable through Lisp which is kind of cool.
Much better than vimscript, but people like
vim's modal editing, so there's an
emacs plugin called evil mode which gives
you vim modal editing within Emacs so
it's not necessarily a binary choice you
can kind of combine both tools if you
want to. And it's worth exploring
both if you have the time.
Next question
Any tips or tricks for machine
learning applications?
I think, like knowing how
a lot of these tools, mainly the data wrangling
a lot of the shell tools, it's really
important because it seems a lot
of what you're doing as machine learning
researcher is trying different things
but I think one core aspect of doing that,
and like a lot of scientific work is being
able to have reproducible results
and logging them in a sensible way
So for example, instead of trying to come
up with really hacky solutions of how
you name your folders to make
sense of the experiments
Maybe it's just worth having for example
what I do is have like a JSON
file that describes the
entire experiment I know like all the parameters
that are within and then I can
really quickly, using the tools that
we have covered, query for all the
experiments that have some specific
purpose or use some data set
Things like that. Apart from that, the other
side of this is, if you are running
kind of things for training machine
learning applications and you
are not already using some sort of
cluster, like university or your
company is providing and you're just kind
of manually sshing, like a lot of
labs do, because that's kind of the easy way
It's worth automating a lot of that job
because it might not seem like it but
manually doing a lot of these operations
takes away a lot of your time and also
kind of your mental energy
for running these things
Anymore vim tips?
I have one. So in the vim lecture we tried
not to link you to too many different
vim plugins because we didn't want that
lecture to be overwhelming but I think
it's actually worth exploring vim plugins
because there are lots and lots
of really cool ones out there.
One resource you can use is the
different instructors dotfiles like a lot
of us, I think I use like two dozen
vim plugins and I find a lot of them quite
helpful and I use them every day
we all use slightly different subsets of
them. So go look at what we use or look
at some of the other resources we've linked
to and you might find some stuff useful
A thing to add to that is, I don't think
we went into a lot detail in the
lecture, correct me if I'm wrong. It's
getting familiar with the leader key
Which is kind of a special key
that a lot of programs will
especially plugins, that will link to
and for a lot of the common operations
vim has short ways of doing it, but you
can just figure out like quicker
versions for doing them. So for example, like
I know that you can do like semicolon WQ
to save and exit or that you
can do like capital ZZ but I
just actually just do leader (which for
me is the space) and then W. And I have
done that for a lot of a lot of kind of
common operations that I keep doing all
the time. Because just saving one keystroke
for an extremely common operation
is just saving thousands a month
Yeah just to expand a little bit
on what the leader key is so in vim you
can bind some keys I can do like ctrl J
does something like holding one key and
then pressing another I can bind that to
something or I can bind a single keystroke
to something. What the leader
key lets you do, is bind
So you can assign any key
to be the leader key and
then you can assign leader followed by
some other key to some action so for
example like Jose's leader key is space
and they can combine space and then
releasing space followed by some other
key to an arbitrary vim command so it
just gives you yet another way of binding
like a whole set of key combinations.
Leader key plus kind of any key on
the keyboard to some functionality
I think I've I forget whether
we covered macros in the vim
uh sure but like vim macros are worth
learning they're not that complicated
but knowing that they're there and knowing
how to use them is going to save
you so much time. The other one is something
called marks. So in vim you can
press m and then any letter on your keyboard
to make a mark in that file and
then you can press apostrophe on the
same letter to jump back to the same
place. This is really useful if you're
like moving back and forth
between two different parts of your code
for example. You can mark one as A and
one as B and you can then jump between
them with tick A and tick B.
There's also Ctrl+O which jumps to the previous
place you were in the file no matter
what caused you to move. So for example
if I am in a some line and then I jump
to B and then I jump to A, Ctrl+O will
take me back to B and then back to the
place I originally was. This can also be
handy for things like if you're doing a
search then the place that you
started the search is a part of
that stack. So I can do a search I can
then like step through the results
and like change them and then Ctrl+O
all the way back up to the search
Ctrl+O also lets you move across files so
if I go from one file to somewhere else in
different file and somewhere else in the
first file Ctrl+O will move me back
through that stack and then there's
Ctrl+I to move forward in that
stack and so it's not as though you
pop it and it goes away forever
The command colon earlier is really handy.
So, colon earlier gives you an earlier
version of the same file and it it does
this based on time not based on actions
so for example if you press a bunch of like
undo and redo and make some changes
and stuff, earlier will take a literally
earlier as in time version of your file
and restore it to your buffer. This can
sometimes be good if you like undid and
then rewrote something and then realize
you actually wanted the version that was
there before you started undoing earlier
let's you do this. And there's a plug-in
called undo tree or something like
that There are several of these,
that let you actually explore the full
tree of undo history the vim keeps
because it doesn't just keep a linear history
it actually keeps the full tree
and letting you explore that might in
some cases save you from having to
re-type stuff you typed in the past or
stuff you just forgot exactly what you
had there that used to work and no longer
works. And this is one final one I
want to mention which is, we mentioned
how in vim you have verbs and nouns
right to your verbs like delete or yank
and then you have nouns like next of
this character or percent to swap brackets
and that sort of stuff the
search command is a noun so you can do
things like D slash and then a string
and it will delete up to the next match
of that pattern this is extremely useful
and I use it all the time
One another neat addition on the undo stuff
that I find incredibly valuable in
an everyday basis is that like one of
the built-in functionalities of vim
is that you can specify an undo directory
and if you have a specified an
undo directory by default vim, if you
don't have this enabled, whenever you
enter a file your undo history is
clean, there's nothing in there
and as you make changes and then
undo them you kind of create this
history but as soon as you exit the
file that's lost. Sorry, as soon
as you exit vim, that's lost. However
if you have an undodir, vim is
gonna persist all those changes into
this directory so no matter how many
times you enter and leave that history
is persisted and it's incredibly
helpful because even like
it can be very helpful for
some files that you modify
often because then you can kind of keep
the flow. But it's also sometimes really
helpful if you modify your bashrc see and
something broke like five days later and
then you've vim again. Like what actually
did I change ,if you don't
have say like version control, then
you can just check the undos and
that's actually what happened. And
the last one, it's also really
worth familiarizing yourself with registers
and what different special
registers vim uses. So for example if
you want to copy/paste really that's
gone into in a specific register and if you
want to for example use the a OS a copy
like the OS clipboard, you should
be copying or yanking
copying and pasting from a different register
and there's a lot of them and yeah
I think that you should explore, there's
a lot of things to know about registers
The next question is asking about two-factor
authentication and I'll just give
a very quick answer to this one in the interest
of time. So it's worth using two
factor auth for anything security sensitive
so I use it for my GitHub
account and for my email and stuff like
that. And there's a bunch of different
types of two-factor auth. From SMS based
to factor auth where you get special
like a number texted to you when you try
to log in you have to type that number
and to other tools like universal to
factor this is like those Yubikeys
that you plug into your you have
to tap it every time you login
so not all, (yeah Jon is holding a
Yubikey), not all two-factor auth is
created equal and you really want to be
using something like U2F rather than SMS
based to factor auth. There something
based on one-time pass codes that you
have to type in we don't have time to get
into the details of why some methods
are better than others but at a high
level use U2F and the Internet has
plenty of explanations for why other
methods are not a great idea
Last question, any comments on differences
between web browsers?
Yes
Differences between web browsers, there
are fewer and fewer differences between
web browsers these day. At this point
almost all web browsers are chrome
Either because you're using Chrome or
because you're using a browser that's
using the same browser engine as Chrome.
It's a little bit sad, one might say, but
I think these days whether you choose
Chrome is a great browser for security reasons
if you want to have something
that's more customizable or
you don't want to be tied to Google then
use Firefox, don't use Safari it's a
worse version of Chrome. The new Internet
Explorer edge is pretty decent and also
uses the same browser engine as
Chrome and that's probably fine
although avoid it if you can because it
has some like legacy modes you don't
want to deal with. I think that's
Oh, there's a cool new browser called flow
that you can't use for anything useful
yet but they're actually writing
their own browser engine and that's really neat
Firefox also has this project called servo which is
they're really implementing their browser engine
in Rust in order to write it to be like
super concurrent and what they've done
is they've started to take modules
from that version and port them
over to gecko or integrate them with gecko
which is the main browser engine
for Firefox just to get those
speed ups there as well
and that's a neat neat thing
you can be watching out for
That is all the questions, hey we did it. Nice
I guess thanks for taking the missing semester
class and let's do it again next year